How are you doing on your presentation?
Fine. I’m just about to work on the ending
and finish the presentation
The conclusion is very important
because it’s the last part of the presentation
It should be short and impressive.
I totally agree
That’s why I want to wrap up
with a powerful conclusion
Do you have any suggestions?
Sure. When you are ready to give your conclusion
you could signal the audience by saying
“That brings me to the end of the presentation.”
Or “That’s all the time I have.”
And the audience will know it’s about time
to conclude the presentation.
Yes. Then you should repeat the main points
and reinforce what you have already said
I can sum up the core message
for the audience to remember
Have you heard of the use of “bookends”
in a presentation?
Isn’t a bookend something you put
at the ends of books to hold them up?
Right. So to “bookend” a presentation
means to place the first “bookend” in the opening
and the second “bookend” at the end
For instance, use a quote in the opening
and then end with another quote
Or ask a question in the beginning
and give the answer at the end
Right. Tell a story during the opening
but hold the ending until the conclusion
This kind of “bookend” presentation
will bring the ending back to the opening
and complete a circle
It will result in a more memorable ending
That’s a very smart idea
By doing this, we can remind the audience
when we first introduced the topic
and what we expected them to learn
from the presentation
And then the conclusion is not
only a review of the main points
but also a checklist to see
if you covered the entire message
you wanted to convey to the audience.
Wonderful
I’ll go back and start working on my conclusion right away